Finding Aid for Edward Henry Kraus pamphlets and reprints, 1902-1949
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward Henry Kraus pamphlets and reprints 1902-1949
Kraus, Edward Henry, 1875-
DA 2; K91; P186
Professor of Mineralogy at the University of Michigan; reprints of scientific articles and other writings.
1 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was assembled from a number of sources.
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Edward H. Kraus was born in 1875 in Syracuse, NY to German parents. He earned his B.S. in 1896 and his M.S. in 1898, both from Syracuse University. He taught at Syracuse University for two years before going to Germany, where he studied mineralogy, geology, and chemistry at the University of Munich. He earned a Doctor of Philosophy in 1901, and returned to the Syracuse to teach mineralogy.
Kraus joined the faculty of the University of Michigan in 1904, where he stayed for the rest of his academic career. He was a Professor of Mineralogy and also served as Dean of the Summer Session, 1915-1933, Dean of the College of Pharmacy, 1923-1933, and Dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, 1933-1945. He retired in 1945 from teaching but maintained an office at the university. He continued his research and publishing until 1970.
Edward Kraus was considered to be an international authority on crystallography and mineralogy. He was the author of five textbooks and numerous scientific papers on mineralogy and crystallography. He was also a founding member and first president of the Mineralogical Society of America in 1919. He also served as president or chairman of many organizations on the national, state, and city levels and at the University of Michigan. These organizations had various focuses, including mineralogy, pharmacy, science in general, honor societies, and higher education.
Edward Kraus died in 1973 at the age of 97.
The Edward Henry Kraus pamphlets and reprints collection consists of reprints of scientific articles, Kraus' memorials on several prominent mineralogists, article on the new mineralogical laboratory at the University of Michigan and the early history of the Mineralogical Society of America, and other writings.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Mineralogy Laboratory.; Mineralogy.
- Pamphlets and reprints
  - Calculating jolly balance. July, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Chemical composition of Bornite and its relation to other sulpho-minerals. June 1914 (Box 1)
  - Combined curriculum in pharmacy and medicine. April 1924 (Box 1)
  - Datalite from Westfield, Massachusetts. [With Cook] July 1906 (Box 1)
  - Datolite from Great Notch, New Jersey. June 1915 (Box 1)
  - Development of pharmaceutical education. May 30, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Die Anderungen des optischen Axenwinkels im Glauberit mit der Temperatur. 1913 (Box 1)
  - Die optischen Eigenschaften einiger Bleisilikate. 1912 (Box 1)
  - Eine neue Jolly'sche federwage zur Bestimmung des spezifishon Gewichts. 1911 (Box 1)
  - First ten years of the Mineralogical Society of America. March 1930 (Box 1)
  - Gemology in North America (Box 1)
    [Page 383, Spring 1947 "Gems and gemology".]
  - Graduate school. (Box 1)
  - Hussakite, a new mineral, and its relation to Xebi ime. July 1902 (Box 1)
  - Iodyrite from Tonopah, Nevada and Broken Hill, South Wales. March 1909 (Box 1)
  - Jodyrit von Tonopah, Nevada und Broken Hill, New South Wales. 1909 (Box 1)
  - Krausite, a new sulfate from California. September 1931 (Box 1)
  - Lead Silicates. April 1912 (Box 1)
  - Manganhaltiget Albit von Kalifornien. 1915 (Box 1)
  - Memorial of Frank Robertson van Horn. March 1934 (Box 1)
  - Memorial of Friedrich J.K. Becke. June 1932 (Box 1)
  - Memorial of Paul Heinrich von Groth. March 1928 (Box 1)
  - Memorial of Reinhard Brauns. March 1938 (Box 1)
  - Might of a crystal. October 28, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Mineralogy for students of Dentistry. December 1922 (Box 1)
  - Mineralogy. June 1941 (Box 1)
  - New mineralogical laboratory at the University Of Michigan. May 1919 (Box 1)
  - New uses for old materials. Undated (Box 1)
  - Notable centennial in American mineralogy. March 1938 (Box 1)
  - Note on the variable composition of Melanochalcite. February 1916 (Box 1)
  - Occur[r]ence and distribution of Celestite-bearing rocks. April 1905 (Box 1)
  - Opportunities for summer study. March 18, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Origin of the Sulphur deposits at the Woolmigh Quarry, Monroe County Mich. One the occurrence and distribution of Celestite bearing rocks. Undated. (Box 1)
  - Presentation of the first Roebling medal of the Mineralogical Society of America to Charles Palache. January 1938 (Box 1)
  - Presentation of the Roebling medal of the Mineralogical Society of America to Paul Niggli. 1948 (Box 1)
  - Presentation of the Roebling medal of the Mineralogical Society to Edward H. Kraus...Acceptance....by Kraus. 1945 (Box 1)
  - Presidential address: Some problems in pharmaceutical education. October 1926 (Box 1)
  - Seamanite, an new manganese phosphor-borate from Iron County, Michigan. June 1930 (Box 1)
  - Some new thermo-optical observations on gypsum and glauberite. [With Peck] 1917 (Box 1)
  - Some pertinent aspects of higher education. July 1931 (Box 1)
  - Some unusual specimens of "float" copper. February 1924 (Box 1)
  - Standardizing the nomenclature of gems. [Page 147, Spring 1949 "Gems and gemology".] (Box 1)
  - Symposium on diamonds. December 1941, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Third symposium on diamonds. 1946 (Box 1)
  - Uber Anglesit von dem Tinticdistrict, Utah. 1916 (Box 1)
  - Uber Datolith von Westfield, Mass. 1906 (Box 1)
  - Uber die Anderungen des optischen Achsenwinkels in Gips mit der Temperatur. 1912 (Box 1)
  - Uber die chemische Zusammensetzung des Buntkupfererzes und dessen Beziehung zu einer nueun Klasifikation der Sulfomineralien. 1914 (Box 1)
  - Unfolding crystal. October 27, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Variation of hardness in the diamond. 1939 (Box 1)
  - Vorkommen von Schwefel und Colestin bei Maybee, Michigan 1906 (Box 1)
  - World responsibilities of education. October 1944 (Box 1)